Register to the Nathaniel Weyl Papers, 1920-2004
Hoover Institution Archives
- Speeches and Writings, 1930-2004; 14-42 (Box 14-42: 7)
  - American Statesmen on Slavery and the Negro, (co-author with William Marina), 1971 (Folder 33: 5)
  - "Aztec Serpent, Russian Bear" (projected history of Mexican Communist Party, uncompleted), 1971 (Folder 33-34)
    - Publisher correspondence (Folder 33: 6)
    - Working and background materials (Folder 33: 7)
    - Working and background materials (contd.) (Folder 34: 1)
    - Reviews and publicity materials (Folder 34: 2)
  - "Weyl on the Subject" newspaper columns, Palm Beach Gold Coasting, 1971 (Folder 34: 3)
  - "Racial Discrimination and the Conservative Outlook," Mankind Quarterly, 1972 January-March (Folder 34: 4)
  - "Evolution and Ethics," Mankind Quarterly, 1972 July-September (Folder 34: 5)
  - Envy and Aristocide in Underdeveloped Countries, circa 1972 (Folder 34: 6)
  - "An Essay on Evolution and Ethics" (projected book, uncompleted), 1972 (Folder 34: 7)
    Proposal and publisher correspondence
  - "Integration: The Dream That Failed" (projected book, uncompleted), 1972 (Folder 34: 8)
    Publisher correspondence and drafts
  - "McGovern, Foreign Policy and Communism" (projected book, uncompleted), 1972 (Folder 34: 9)
    Publisher correspondence
  - "Israel and South Africa: Two Beleaguered Elites," Mankind Quarterly, 1973 January-March (Folder 34: 10)
  - "Population Control and the Anti-Eugenic Ideology," Mankind Quarterly, 1973 October-December (Folder 34: 11)
  - "The Impact of Famine on I.Q.," Mankind Quarterly, circa 1973 (Folder 34: 12)
  - Newspaper columns, Manchester Union Leader, 1973 (Folder 34: 13)
  - "The Importance of Passport Fraud in Internal Security," speech, Public Affairs Luncheon Club of Dallas, Texas, 1974 February 18 (Folder 34: 14)
    Draft and program
  - "An Analysis of the 1972 Mensa Membership," Mensa Research Journal, 1974 July (Folder 34: 15)
  - "Natural Selection through Slavery and the African Slave Trade," Mankind Quarterly, 1974 July-September (Folder 34: 16)
  - Projected study of 19th century Russian writer Sonia Kovalevskaia and/or translation of her novel, to be co-authored with Sylvia Weyl (uncompleted), 1974 (Folder 34: 17)
    Publisher correspondence, working materials, and drafts
  - Newspaper columns, Manchester Union Leader, 1975 (Folder 35: 1)
  - "Disease as a Eugenic Force" and "A Note on the Black Death," Mankind Quarterly, 1976 April-June (Folder 35: 2)
  - "Aristocide under Fuehrers and Commissars," Modern Age, 1975 Summer (Folder 35: 3)
    Printed copy and press coverage
  - Notes on the Laetolil Find and Prehominid Raciation, 1975 November 17 (Folder 35: 4)
  - Newspaper columns, Manchester Union Leader, 1975 (Folder 35: 5)
  - "Disease as a Eugenic Force" and "A Note on the Black Death," Mankind Quarterly, 1976 April-June (Folder 35: 6)
  - "A Biogenetic Paradigm of Western Civilization,"Mankind Quarterly, 1976 July-September (Folder 35: 7)
  - "Stuart Cloete, 1897-1976" (obituary), Mankind Quarterly, 1976 July-September (Folder 35: 8)
  - Newspaper columns, Manchester Union Leader, 1976 (Folder 35: 9)
  - "Survival Past the Century Mark," Mankind Quarterly, 1977 January-March (Folder 35: 10)
  - "Pelvic Brim and Cranial Size," Mankind Quarterly, 1977 October-December (Folder 35: 11)
  - "New Revelations in Alger Hiss Case," Human Events, 1977 November 12 (Folder 35: 12)
  - "Aristocide: The War against Human Ability,", circa 1977 (Folder 35: 13-14)
  - "Aristocide: The War against Human Ability,", circa 1977 (Folder 36: 1-2)
    Drafts (contd.)
  - Newspaper columns, Manchester Union Leader, 1977 (Folder 36: 3)
  - "World Population Growth and the Geography of Intelligence," Modern Age, 1978 Winter (Folder 36: 4)
  - "Canada Charged with Red Spy Cover-up" (re Igor Gouzenko), Human Events, 1978 April 15 (Folder 36: 5)
  - "The Triumph of Folly: Carter and South Africa," Mankind Quarterly, 1978 April-June (Folder 36: 6)
  - "Jewish and Chinese Leadership in American Science" (co-author with Sylvia Weyl), Mankind Quarterly, 1978 July-September (Folder 36: 7)
  - Human Variation: The Biopsychology of Age, Race, and Sex,(co-editor with R. Travis Osborne and Clyde E. Noble), 1978 (Folder 36: 8)
    Correspondence with co-editors, reviews, and publicity materials
  - Newspaper columns, Manchester Union Leader, 1978 (Folder 36: 9)
  - "Karl Marx Was No Abe Lincoln," Human Events, 1979 January 20 (Folder 36: 10)
  - "Jewish Scientists in America," Midstream, 1979 April (Folder 36: 11)
  - Karl Marx, Mexico and Manifest Destiny, circa 1979 (Folder 36: 12)
  - Karl Marx, Racist, 1979 (Folder 36: 13)
    Publisher correspondence and agreement, and reviews
  - Newspaper columns, Manchester Union Leader, 1979 (Folder 36: 14)
  - "The Allopatric Instinct, Germinal Selection and the Negro,", circa 1970s (Folder 37: 1)
  - Genocide and Aristocide in Totalitarian Systems, circa 1970s (Folder 37: 2)
  - "Subversion," in Encyclopaedia Americana, circa 1970s (Folder 37: 3)
  - Using Monozygotic and Dizygotic Twin Pairs to Measure the Dispersion Effect of Heredity, Intelligence, circa 1970s (Folder 37: 4)
  - China and the American Communist Labyrinth, 1980 June 19 (Folder 37: 5)
  - "Lenin: Dwarf or Demigod" (projected book, uncompleted), 1980 (Folder 37: 6)
    Proposal and bibliographic notes
  - Newspaper columns, Manchester Union Leader, 1980 (Folder 37: 7)
  - The Institute for Policy Studies and Soviet Intelligence, 1981 March 7 (Folder 37: 8)
  - "Karl Marx's Fantasies," Midstream, 1981 March (Folder 37: 9)
  - "The Realm of Envy" (re Israeli-Arab relations), 1981 July 16 (Folder 37: 10)
  - "The Espionage Case of Alger Hiss" (commissioned by Regnery Gateway but never published), 1981 (Folder 37)
    - Publisher correspondence and agreement (Folder 37: 11)
    - Drafts (Folder 37: 12-15)
  - The KGB Connections: An Investigation into Soviet Operations in North America (television documentary), 1981 (Folder 37-38)
    Includes interviews with Weyl, Hede Massing and others
    - Press release and press coverage (Folder 37: 16)
    - Transcripts (Folder 38: 1)
  - Newspaper columns, Manchester Union Leader, 1981 (Folder 38: 2)
  - "Israel and Francisco Franco," Midstream, 1982 February (Folder 38: 3)
  - Are Americans Getting Brighter or Stupider?, 1982 March 23 (Folder 38: 4)
  - Ethnic Breakdown of 1982 Mensa Membership" and "Marital Status and Sex Breakdown, 1982 November 15 (Folder 38: 5)
    Typescripts and data
  - "The Japanese Century?" Mensa Bulletin, 1982 November (Folder 38: 6)
  - "Nabobs and Parasites" (re Jewish wealth in America), 1982 (Folder 38: 7)
  - "The Marx-Hitler-Holocaust Enigma," Midstream, 1983 November (Folder 38: 8)
  - "Implications of Changing Pelvic Brim for Brain Size and Human Intelligence," Eugenics Bulletin, 1984 Fall (Folder 38: 9)
  - Why Was Marcel Proust a Homosexual?, 1985 July 13 (Folder 38: 10)
  - How Chess Was Invented, 1985 November 14 (Folder 38: 11)
  - The Geography of American Achievement, 1989 (Folder 38: 12)
  - The Cambridge Traitors at High Tide, 1930-1950, circa 1980s (Folder 38: 13)
  - Memoirs of the Communist Labyrinth, circa 1980s (Folder 38: 14)
  - Memoirs of the Communist Labyrinth, circa 1980s (Folder 39: 1-5)
    Typescript (contd.)
  - Memoirs of the Communist Labyrinth, circa 1980s (Folder 40: 1)
  - Some Possible Political Implications of Eugenics, circa 1980s (Folder 40: 2)
  - Wonderings: A Collection of Sonnets, 1992 (Folder 40: 3)
  - Sarpedon and Other Poems, 1993/1994 (Folder 40: 4)
  - The Omega Poems, 1999 (Folder 40: 5)
  - Is This the Face...? and Other Poems, 2001 (Folder 40: 6)
  - Encounters with Communism, 2003 (Folder 40)
    - Drafts (Folder 40: 7)
    - Printed copy (Folder 40: 8)
  - To Live in Delphi and Other Poems, 2003 (Folder 40: 9)
  - "Adoption Fifty Years Ago" (autobiographical vignette), 2004 September 21 (Folder 40: 10)
  - "Ghosts of Revolution: Ralph Bates" (autobiographical vignette), 2004 December 10 (Folder 40: 11)
  - "The Wallings" (autobiographical vignette), 2004 December 12 (Folder 40: 12)
  - "A Trip to Lebanon by Freighter" (autobiographical vignette), 2004 December 17 (Folder 40: 13)
  - Those Effete Aristocrats, 2004 December 23 (Folder 40: 14)
  - "A Few Brief Encounters with Anti-Semitism" (autobiographical vignette), circa 2000s (Folder 40: 15)
  - "Three Days in a Country Once Called Rhodesia" (autobiographical vignette), circa 2000s (Folder 40: 16)
  - "A Voyage to Suriname" (autobiographical vignette), circa 2000s (Folder 40: 17)
  - Book reviews (Folder 41-42)
    - Typescript reviews of books about communism and subversion, circa 1954-1979 (Folder 41: 1)
      Includes review of John Chabot Smith, Alger Hiss (1976)
    - Typescript reviews of books about Latin America, circa 1941-1965 (Folder 41: 2-3)
    - Typescript reviews of books about race and genetics, circa 1957-1966 (Folder 41: 4)
    - Typescript reviews of books on miscellaneous subjects, 1958-1982 (Folder 41: 5)
    - Printed copies of reviews in Mankind Quarterly, circa 1961-1966 (Folder 41: 6)
    - Printed copies of reviews in Midstream, 1979-1985 (Folder 41: 7-8)
    - Printed copies of reviews in Modern Age, 1971-1982 (Folder 42: 1)
    - Printed copies of reviews in The Nation, 1938 (Folder 42: 2)
    - Printed copies of reviews in National Review, 1961-1976 (Folder 42: 3)
    - Printed copies of reviews in Palm Beach Gold Coasting, circa 1962-1966 (Folder 42: 4)
    - Printed copies of reviews in other publications, 1941-1981 (Folder 42: 5)
  - Letters to the editor (Folder 42)
    Typescripts and printed copies
    - Letters to the editor re communism and subversion, 1950-1980 (Folder 42: 6)
      Includes a letter written under the pseudonym Norman Walters
    - Letters to the editor re Latin America, 1960-1962 (Folder 42: 7)
      mainly responses to commentary on Red Star over Cuba
    - Letters to the editor re race and genetics, 1960-1983 (Folder 42: 8)
    - Letters to the editor on miscellaneous subjects, 1962-1984 (Folder 42: 9)
- Subject File, 1920-1984; 43-49 (Box 43-49: 9)
  Mainly printed matter, with some memoranda, notes and correspondence.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Argentina. Printed matter, 1961-1966, mainly re communism in Argentina (Folder 43: 1)
  - Brain chemistry. Printed matter, 1965-1971 (Folder 43: 2)
  - Bunche, Ralph. Memoranda by Weyl, notes, and clippings, 1957, re alleged Communist connections of Bunche (Folder 43: 3)
  - Chessmasters. Notes and printed matter, 1969-1973 (Folder 43: 4)
  - China. Notes and printed matter, 1945-1975 (Folder 43: 5)
  - Communism and subversion (Folder 43)
    - Memoranda by Weyl, 1950-1970 (Folder 43: 6)
      Includes memoranda of conversations with Federal Bureau of Investigation agents and memoranda apparently intended for Federal Bureau of Investigation use
    - Communist Party manuals, undated (Folder 43: 7)
    - Printed matter and notes, 1938-1921 (Folder 43: 8)
  - Communist International (Folder 43-44)
    - International Press Correspondence issues
      - 1928 (Folder 43: 9-10)
      - 1932-1933 (Folder 43: 11)
      - 1934 (Folder 44: 1)
    - World News and Views issues, 1938 (Folder 44: 2)
  - Crime and violence. Memoranda, notes, and printed matter, 1955-1975, re biological bases for crime and violence (Folder 44: 3)
  - Cuba (Folder 44)
    - Memoranda by Weyl re political situation in Cuba and prospects for counter-revolution, 1960-1966, possibly intended for Central Intelligence Agency use. (Folder 44: 4)
      Includes memorandum by Weyl of conversation with Alberto Gandero and memoranda by Jeanne Perry transcribing her conversations with Weyl
    - Typescript studies (not by Weyl) re communism and political situation in Cuba, 1959-1960 (Folder 44: 5)
      Mainly in Spanish
    - Printed matter ans notes, 1959-1970 (Folder 44: 6)
  - Debs, Eugene V. Printed copy of Ruth Le Prade, ed., Debs and the Poets, inscribed by Debs to Sylvia Castleton (later Sylvia Weyl), 1920 (Folder 45: 1)
  - Disease. Printed matter and notes, 1942-1969, mainly re genetic factors in disease (Folder 45: 2)
  - Dominican Republic. Memoranda and printed matter, 1958-1962 (Folder 45: 3)
    Includes printed speeches of Rafael Trujillo, and memoranda by Weyl re bribery of American government officials by the Dominican government of General Trujillo
  - Dozenberg, Nicholas. Mimeographed statement re espionage operations by Dozenberg, 1949 (Folder 45: 4)
  - Envy. Notes by Weyl re envy as political motive, 1970 (Folder 45: 5)
  - Ergot. Printed matter, 1970 (Folder 45: 6)
  - Galois, Evariste. Notes and printed matter re the early 19th century French revolutionary Galois, 1903 and undated (Folder 45: 7)
  - Galton, Sir Francis. Notes, printed matter and bibliographical data re Galton, 1914-1971 (Folder 45: 8)
  - Genetics. Printed matter and notes, 1933-1982 (Folder 45-46: 9)
  - Hiss, Alger (Folder 45)
    - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Folder 45: 10)
      Includes correspondence re role of Julian Wadleigh, and correspondence with Victor Lasky and others re projected book by Lasky in collaboration with Weyl about Hiss.
      Includes draft review of The Unfinished Case of Alger Hiss by Fred J. Cook prepared by Weyl for Lasky
    - Memoranda and notes, 1940-1980, mainly by Weyl (Folder 46: 1)
      Includes draft review by Hede Massing of Perjury: The Hiss-Chambers Case by Allen Weinstein
    - Printed matter, 1957-1980 (Folder 46: 2-4)
  - Immigration. Printed matter and notes, 1957-1968 (Folder 46: 5)
  - Insanity. Printed matter, 1959-1972, re genetic factors in insanity (Folder 46: 6)
  - Intelligence. Printed matter and notes, 1929-1984 (Folder 46: 7-8)
  - Intelligence. Printed matter and notes, 1929-1984 (contd.) (Folder 47: 1)
  - International Foundation for Gifted Children. Correspondence, minutes, memoranda, proposals, and printed matter, 1968-1979 (Folder 47: 2)
  - Jews (Folder 47)
    - Notes, 1955-1959 and undated (Folder 47: 3-4)
    - Printed matter, 1956-1979 (Folder 47: 5-6)
  - Kennedy, John F. Printed matter, 1976-1977, in part re conspiracy theories of assassination (Folder 47: 7)
  - Kissinger, Henry A. Notes and printed matter, 1974-1977, mainly re allegations that Kissinger was a Soviet agent (Folder 47: 8)
  - Latin America. Notes and printed matter, 1953-1961 (Folder 48: 1)
  - Lead poisoning in history. Notes and printed matter, 1953-1961 (Folder 48: 2)
  - Middle East. Memoranda and printed matter, 1970 (Folder 48: 3)
  - Mongols. Notes and printed matter, 1956-1963 (Folder 48: 4)
  - Münzenberg, Willi. Printed article, 1965 (Folder 48: 5)
  - Nuclear freeze movement. Printed matter, 1981-1982 (Folder 48: 6)
  - Nutrition. Printed matter, 1961-1971, mainly re effects on heredity (Folder 48: 7)
  - Oceanography. Printed matter and notes, 1968-1969 (Folder 48: 8)
  - Origins of man. Printed matter, notes and correspondence, 1958-1971 (Folder 48: 9)
  - Panama. Memorandum on political situation, 1964 (Folder 48: 10)
  - Race. Printed matter and notes, 1957-1981, especially re blacks (Folder 48: 11-12)
  - Reds (Motion picture). Notes and printed matter, 1982 (Folder 49: 1)
    Includes photocopy of letter from John Reed to Walter Weyl, circa 1910s
  - Rosenberg, Julius and Ethel. Printed matter, undated (Folder 49: 2)
  - Sex ratio in births. Printed matter, 1935-1970 (Folder 49: 3)
  - Soviet Union. Printed matter and notes, 1962-1983 (Folder 49: 4)
  - Venezuela. Printed matter and correspondence, 1961 and undated, re communism in Venezuela (Folder 49: 5)
  - Villaggio del Superdotato. Correspondence, reports, and printed matter, 1967-1969, re charitable institution for gifted children in Sicily (Folder 49: 6)
  - Wieland, William. Memorandum and clippings, 1960-1965 (Folder 49: 7)
  - Miscellany (Folder 49)
    - Financial and personal documents, 1972-1981 (Folder 49: 8)
    - Printed matter, 1963-1980 (Folder 49: 9)
- Audiovisual File, circa 1950-1978; 50 (Box 50: 9)
  Photographs, sound recordings, and microfilm
  - Photographs, circa 1950-1971 (Folder 50: 1)
    Includes photographs of Nathaniel and Sylvia Weyl and of the Villaggio del Superdotato
  - Recording disc, 1963, entitled "Operation Samovar" (Folder 50: 2)
  - Audio cassettes of conversations between Nathaniel and Sylvia Weyl and Robert Gorham and Hope Davis, 1978 (Folder 50: 3-4)
  - Microfilm reel of booklet Origine et transformations de l'homme et des autres êtres by P. Trémeaux, 1865 (Folder 50: 5)